A Guide to the Tredegar Iron Works Records, 1801-1957
Library of Virginia
- Appendix B: Agreements and Deeds
  - Series I: Administrative Records (Box 15-16)
    - Real estate files, Deeds, 1893-1898 (Box-folder 16:3)
      - b) 1893 June 28, Agreement between Tredegar and Alleghany Iron Co. for mining of iron ore on the Grace Furnace Property in Botetourt County, Va. (2 copies)
      - c) 1895 August 21, Agreement between Tredegar and Alleghany Iron Co. for mining of iron ore on the Grace Furnace Property in Botetourt County, Va. (2 copies)
      - d) 1897 June 29, Order from Tredegar to Alleghany Iron Co. for pig iron
    - Real estate files, Deeds, 1900-1909 (Box-folder 16:4)
      - a) 1901 January 21, Deed between John Coke, T. William Pemberton and St. George Fitzhugh to Archer Anderson, John Coke and St. George Fitzhugh for land in Duluth, Minnesota (4 copies)
      - b) 1906 February 1, Deed between Archer Anderson, Joseph R. Anderson, J.F. Anderson, and Fannie Hobson, Mary Bruce, Mary Anderson, Ann Archer, Archer Anderson, Joseph Anderson, and John Anderson for land known as the Cloverdale Iron Property, Botetourt County, Va.
      - c) 1907 July 1, Deed between Tredegar and Alleghany Ore & Iron Co. for lease of land at Oriskany, Va. (2 copies)
      - d) 1909 March 17, Contract between Tredegar and Hugh Sorrell for land near Rebecca Furnace in Botetourt County, Va.
      - e) Contract between George Robinson and Tredegar for land near Jane Furnace property in Botetourt County, Va.
      - f) 1909 April 1, Contract between Tredegar and Henry O. Smith for land near Jane Furnace property in Botetourt County, Va.
      - g) 1909 April 3, Contract between Tredegar and Phillip Newcomb for land near Jane Furnace property in Botetourt County, Va.
    - Real estate files, Deeds, 1913-1915 (Box-folder 16:5)
      - a) 1913 March, Deed between Tredegar and Pulaski Iron Co. for lands known as Cloverdale Iron property in Botetourt County, Va.
      - b) 1913 December 9, Agreement between Tredegar and J.E. Lemon for lands known as Grace Furnace property in Oriskany, Va. (2 copies)
      - c) 1915 March 4, Agreement between Tredegar and J.B. Buhrman for land known as Jane Furnace Tract, Botetourt County, Va.
    - Real estate files, Deeds, 1938-1955 (Box-folder 16:6)
      - a) 1938 August 26, Deed of lease between Tredegar and Richard Sloan for home near Jane Furnace property, Botetourt County, Va.
      - b) 1938 September 12, Telephone right of way deeds
      - c) 1938 November 10, Deed of lease between Tredegar and James Preston Sorrell for land near Rebecca Furnace Tract, Botetourt County, Va.
      - d) 1940 February 16, Deed of lease between Tredegar and William M. Hayslett for land near Rebecca Furnace Tract, Botetourt County, Va.
      - e) 1950 March 1, Deed of lease between Tredegar and Albemarle Manufacturing Co. for land in Richmond, Va.
      - f) 1952 April 1, Deed of lease between Tredegar and Albemarle Manufacturing Co. for land in Richmond, Va. (2 copies)
      - g) 1954 June 8, Deed of lease between Tredegar and Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Co. for land in Richmond, Va.
      - h) 1955 August 9, Deed of lease between Tredegar and Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Co. for land in Richmond, Va.
  - Series VIII: Anderson Family Papers (Box 1210)
    Subseries 6: Estate of Joseph R. Anderson
    - Agreements and deeds, 1848-1849 (Box-folder 1210:1)
      - a) 1848 April 4, Bond of Joseph R. Anderson to Nicholas Mills and Holden Rhodes for the sum of $42,200
      - b) 1848 April 4, Bond of Joseph R. Anderson to Nicholas Mills and Holden Rhodes for the sum of $47,200
      - c) 1848 April 4, Bond of Joseph R. Anderson to Nicholas Mills and Holden Rhodes for the sum of $50,000
      - d) 1848 April 4, Bond of Joseph R. Anderson to Nicholas Mills and Holden Rhodes for the sum of $44,800
      - e) 1848 April 4, Bond of Joseph R. Anderson to Nicholas Mills and Holden Rhodes for the sum of $52,200
      - f) 1848 December 14, Indenture between John F. and Cassandra Anderson and William N. and Mary Anderson, of Botetourt County, Va., to Joseph R. Anderson of Richmond, Va., for land surrounding Catawaba Iron Co. in Botetourt County, Va.
      - g) 1849 September 15, Assign to Joseph R. Anderson the interests of W.(?) Nelson, in the claim of Tredegar on the U.S. for cannon rejected by the inspecting officers
    - Agreements and deeds, 1854-1859 (Box-folder 1210:2)
      - a) 1854 January 23, Partnership agreement between Charles Y. Morriss and Joseph R. Anderson
      - b) 1854 July 1, Partnership agreement between Joseph R. Anderson, Mathew Delany, Francis T. Glasgow, and William Steptoe, now called Anderson, Delany & Co.
      - c) 1854 July 31, Power of attorney of John T. Shanks, Grace E. Woodson and William M. Woodson of Botetourt County, Va., to (?) Merrick of Frederick, Md., and Joseph R. Anderson
      - d) 1854 October 28, Contract of Anderson, Delany & Co. with the United States and James C. Dobbin, Sec. of the Navy, to construct on board the U.S. Steamer Roanoke, two steam engines, propellers, and boilers. Includes specifications and list of parts
      - e) 1854, Deed between Joseph R. and Sarah Anderson and Lewis Crenshaw, for lease of 2 lots of land in Richmond, Va., between the James River and James River and Kanawha Canal
      - f) 1855 January 5, Agreement that Joseph R. Anderson sells to R. Archer & Co., stock on hand at the Armory Iron Works
      - g) 1855 February 6, Contract between Anderson, Delany, & Co., Robert Archer and John F. Tanner to manufacture 50 guns of 9 inch caliber
      - h) 1856 February 18, Agreement to cancel the partnership of Joseph R. Anderson, Mathew Delany, Francis T. Glasgow, and William Steptoe (Anderson, Delany & Co.) and return their shares to Joseph R. Anderson
      - i) 1859 January 1, Partnership agreement between Joseph R. Anderson, John Tanner, and Robert Archer to put capital, foundries, machine shops, rolling mill, and Armory mill into Tredegar. Anderson assumed overall direction of company
    - Agreements and deeds, 1861-1868 (Box-folder 1210:3)
      - a) 1861 January 1, Partnership between Joseph R., R. Archer and B.S. Archer into a co-partnership called J.R. Anderson & Co.
      - b) 1862 January 1, Agreement between William Shother, James Jones, R. Milton Cary, and Powhatan Roberts, on one part, and Joseph R. Anderson, on the other part, releasing Anderson the land surrounding Tredegar
      - c) 1862 May 12, Deed from Thomas Steers to Joseph R. Anderson & Co., for 210 acres in Botetourt County, Va.
      - d) 1862 November 3, Deed from George and Susan Wilson and Arthur Burks, to Joseph R. Anderson & Co., for land in Botetourt County, Va.
      - e) 1863 May 7, Deed from John and C.M. Anderson to Joseph R. Anderson & Co., for lands attached to Cloverdale Furnace property in Botetourt County, Va.
      - f) 1863 September 5, Deed from Samuel Oberhaun and Joseph R. Anderson & Co., for land in Botetourt County, Va.
      - g) 1864 March 30, Agreement from Martha Oberhaun, widow of Samuel, relinquishing her rights to the land in Botetourt County, Va.
      - h) 1864 October 6, Deed from Charles Layborune and Joseph R. Anderson & Co., land in Botetourt County, Va., to get iron ore at "Velly (?) Tract"
      - i) 1866 January 26, Deed from Francis Thomas of Allegany County, Md., to Joseph R. Anderson, lots of land in Allegany County, Md.
      - j) 1866 April 9, Deed from Joseph H. Scranton and Cornelia W. Scranton of Luzerne County, Pa., to Joseph R. Anderson, lots of land in Allegany County, Md.
      - k) 1866 November 13, Deed from George and E. Fannie Bosher of Henrico County, Va., and Thomas Sydnor of Hanover County, Va. for land in New Kent County, Va.
      - l) 1866 November 13, Deed between Samuel Cottrell and Charles M. Bosher, and George Bosher, and David Baker, for land in New Kent County, Va.
      - m) 1866 November 19, Deed between William Schley, Josias Pennington and Joseph R. Anderson all are tenants of land in Allegany County, Md., for partition of joined lands in Allegany County, Md.
      - n) 1866 December 12, Agreement between Johns Hopkins, George H. Williams, William A. Fisher, and Joseph R. Anderson, for land in Allegany County, Md.
      - o) 1868 May 27, Deed between Joseph Scranton and Joseph R. Anderson, for land in Allegany County, Md.
    - Agreements and deeds, 1871-1878 (Box-folder 1210:4)
      - a) 1871 June 26, Assignment to Joseph R. Anderson the right, title and interest of the Farmers Bank of Va.
      - b) 1871 October 25, Deed between Josiah Gordon and Joseph R. Anderson, for land in Allegany County, Md.
      - c) 1873 October 7, Deed between Tredegar Co. and Isaac Davenport for Tredegar bonds
      - d) 1876 April 10, Deed of trust between Joseph R. Anderson, Archer Anderson, Robert Archer, and Isaac Davenport, Jr. and J.H. Carrington
      - e) 1877 January 24, Agreement between Alexander H. Rutherford and Joseph R. Anderson regarding bonds
      - f) 1878 July 27, Deed of release from Isaac Davenport and J.H. Carrington to Joseph R. Anderson
      - g) 1878 July 27, Deed of trust between Joseph R. Anderson and Austin Boulware and Charles Williams
      - h) 1882 February 2, Sale of 100 shares of The Richmond and Danville Extension Co. by Joseph R. Anderson
    - Agreements and deeds, 1880-1886 (Box-folder 1210:5)
      - a) 1880 April 1, Deed of trust on Catawaba Iron Co. land, between J.H. Bramwill and W.A. Glasgow and T.F. Glasgow
      - b) 1880 April 1, Deed between Joseph R. Anderson & Co. to J.H. Bramwill, land around Catawba creek
      - c) 1880 April 26, Deed of release between Isaac Davenport and Isaac Carrington, and Joseph R. Anderson, Archer Anderson, and Robert Archer
      - d) 1881 January 6, Deed of release between Wellington Goddin and Wood Bouldin, Alexander H. Rutherford, and Joseph R. Anderson
      - e) 1881 April 28, Deed for Montevue Mining and Manufacturing Company
      - f) 1881, Special warranty deed from Mason family to William E. Snails
      - g) 1882 July 7, Deed from William Tanner to Joseph R. Anderson, for land including Cloverdale Furnace Tract, Botetourt County, Va.
      - h) 1882 July 24, Deed between Margaret Goodwin et. al to Joseph R. Anderson, for land including Cloverdale Furnace Tract
      - i) 1885 February 13, Contract between Joseph R. Anderson and James Mundy, for the Mount Joy Farm in Botetourt County, Va.
      - j) 1885 May 13, Deed of conveyance between John Allen, agent for the board of supervisors of Botetourt County, Va. to Joseph R. Anderson, for Mount Joy Farm in Botetourt County, Va.
      - k) 1886 December 22, Deed between James Mundy and W.A. Glasgow, for land in Botetourt County, Va.
    - Agreements, 1887-1889 (Box-folder 1210:6)
      - a) 1887 February 14, Deed between Matthew Harrison, Egbert Handy, and Joseph R. Anderson, for land in St. Louis County, Minnesota
      - b) 1887 June 11, Deed between Joseph Anderson and J.C. Leake, for Mount Joy farm, Botetourt County, Va.
      - c) 1887 July 7, Deed between Joseph F. Anderson and Joseph R. Anderson, for land in Duluth, Minnesota
      - d) 1887 July 28, Deed between Frank T. Glasgow and Joseph R. Anderson, for Mount Joy farm in Botetourt County, Va.
      - e) 1887, Agreement between Matthew Harrison and Joseph R. Anderson, for land in Douglas County, Wisconsin, 1887
      - f) 1889 May 2, Deed of trust from R.W. Montague
    - Agreements and deeds, 1890-1892 (Box-folder 1210:7)
      - a) 1890 March 26, Bond between Joseph R. Anderson and James Dooley, Peter Mayo and Joseph Ruan, trustees for the Richmond and St. Paul Land and Improvement Association
      - b) 1890 May 12, Deed between Charles H. Stevens and John Coke, T. William Pemberton, and St. George R. Fitzhugh, for land in St. Louis County, Minnesota
      - c) 1890 August 14, Deed between Matthew Harrison and Joseph R. Anderson and John T. Anderson, for land in St. Louis, Minnesota
      - d) 1890 August 14, Testament from Joseph R. Anderson regarding with Matthew Harrison, for land in St. Louis, Minnesota
      - e) 1890 August 14, Deed between Joseph R. Anderson and Matthew Harrison, for land in St. Louis, Minnesota
      - f) 1891 March 30, Deed between Joseph R. Anderson and John Anderson and the Iron Car Equipment Co.
      - g) 1891 July 14, Deed of release between Post, Martin & Co., and John Anderson and Joseph Anderson
      - h) 1891 August 10, Deed between Cullen, Coke, Pemberton, Brown, and Saunders family, and Joseph R. Anderson, for land in Douglas County, Wisconsin
      - i) 1892 October 15, Agreement between John T. Anderson and Jackson Brandt & Co. for land on West Franklin St., Richmond, Va.
      - j) 1892 October 25, Agreement regarding the settlement of Joseph R. Anderson's estate between Mary Pegram Anderson, children of Joseph R. Anderson, and Archer Anderson, administrator of the estate (2 copies)
      - k) 1893 June 27, Deed between Ambrose Cox and Matthew Harrison, for land in St. Louis, Minnesota (2 copies)
    - Agreements and deeds, 1893-1930 (Box-folder 1211:1-11)
      Relates to the division of the estate of Joseph R. Anderson by the heirs and Archer Anderson, administrator of the estate of Joseph R. Anderson. Concerns land in Duluth, Minnesota; Washington, D.C.; Maryland; and Virginia, and financial matters. Also includes information on the estate of Matthew B. Harrison, by Lucy Gray Harrison, administrator of his estate.
- Appendix C: Finding aid key
  Items listed under old system of numbers and Roman numerals can be found in the corresponding series of the new finding aid
  - X: Account copying books, 1871-1891
    See Series II: General Accounts
  - 12: Accounts payable, 1924-1956
  - 14: Accounts receivable ledgers, 1924-1951
  - 13: Accounts receivable registers, 1924-1957
  - IX: Balance books, 1870-1898
  - VI, 1, 16: Cash books, 1841-1937
  - VII, 10, 19: Cash books, petty, 1852-1948
  - 15: Cash books, receipts and disbursements, 1924-1956
  - XI: Check books, 1856-1898
  - XXIII: Clearance sheet book, 1900
    See Series III: Production and Labor Records
  - XVII: Consignment book, 1865-1874
    See Series V: Sales and Shipping Records
  - XIII: Contract books, 1859-1915
  - V, 8, 9: Day books, 1836-1924
  - XXII: Inventory books, 1860-1917
    See Series IV: Purchasing and Receiving Records
  - XV: Journal books, 1867-1911
  - 11: Journal voucher books, 1924-1957
  - IV: Journals, 1840-1881
  - 18: Ledgers, operating expense, 1924-1941
  - III, 2, 17: Ledgers, general, 1841-1949
  - I, 31: Letter books, out, 1841-1952
    See Series VII: Correspondence, Outgoing
  - XXXII, 32: Letters, incoming, 1872-1957
    See Series VI: Correspondence, Incoming
  - XVIII: Loadings, railroad freight car, 1892
  - XIV: Order books, 1853-1908
  - XXIX, 21: Pay roll ledgers, 1852-1957
  - XXVI: Receipt book, coal, 1879-1885
  - XXV: Receipt book, pig iron, 1861-1864
  - XXVII: Receipt book, pig and scrap iron, 1879-1885
  - XXIV: Receiving book, 1862-1865
  - VIII, 3: Sales, foundry, 1854-1924
  - VIII, 4: Sales, rolling mill, 1844-1922
  - 5: Sales, rolling mill (bar mill), 1919-1924
  - 6: Sales, rolling mill (spike mill), 1922-1924
  - VIII, 7: Sales, shoe, 1873-1924
  - XIX: Shipment of sash weights, 1896
  - XII: Store books, company, 1868-1869
  - XVI: Ticket books, 1847-1908
  - XXVIII: Time books, 1854-1900
  - XXI: Units produced books, 1843-1925
  - XXXIII: Vouchers, 1872-1904
  - XX, 20: Weighers returns, 1889-1901;1923-1938